<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on </title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice</title>
      <link>/post/module_seven/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/module_seven/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Research Methods and Professional Practice module! Here you will find another 12 weeks worth of self reflections, broken down by units.
Below is a small introduction extract from the course&amp;rsquo;s website:
This module aims to provide you with a practical foundation in research methods that will enable you to conduct research in a practical setting. The module covers various tools and techniques that you, as a researcher, may need and allows for feedback throughout the module through cases and project tasks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 12</title>
      <link>/post/m7u12/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u12/</guid>
      <description>Project Management and Managing Risk And that&amp;rsquo;s it, final unit for this project. I won&amp;rsquo;t lie, it&amp;rsquo;s been a long and tough twelve weeks.
This module was no joke; the content was plentiful and abundant. I have had to juggle two modules at the same time for six weeks, while still working full time. Let&amp;rsquo;s just say that I am happy it&amp;rsquo;s coming to an end.
I have definitely learned a lot, but I reserve that for my summative reflections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 11</title>
      <link>/post/m7u11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u11/</guid>
      <description>Going Forward: Professional Development and Your e-Portfolio For this particular unit, we&amp;rsquo;ve had to complete three different documents. This was quite time consuming and I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a couple of days thinking about how best to fill the Action Plan, the SWOT and the Skills Matrix.
For full disclosure, I have never had to do any of those, so it was actually quite hard to get started and to keep going.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 10</title>
      <link>/post/m7u10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u10/</guid>
      <description>Research Writing Nearly there - as I finish unit 10, I am starting to feel tired. This module workload has been beyond everything I&amp;rsquo;ve studied so far for my MSc. The tutor wasn&amp;rsquo;t lying when she said that the module was intense.
You can tell that this week&amp;rsquo;s content tied together all the work I&amp;rsquo;ve done so far. I don&amp;rsquo;t see myself as a strong writer, so I&amp;rsquo;m committed to learn as much as I can from this unit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 9</title>
      <link>/post/m7u9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u9/</guid>
      <description>Validity and Generalisability in Research This week I will not reflect a lot. Again the exercises have been quite challenging as I&amp;rsquo;ve never really used Excel in that manner before.
While I did enjoy doing all the data analysis via the exercises, I won&amp;rsquo;t lie, it was tough. I am by no means a data expert. At least I&amp;rsquo;ve learned new skills in this unit, which is always a plus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 8</title>
      <link>/post/m7u8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u8/</guid>
      <description>Data Analysis and Visualisation Unit 8 shifted our focus from research methods to data analysis and visualisation.
As I looked into the details of handling and making sense of data, I noticed the big differences between quantitative and qualitative data. While quantitative data can be neatly shown using descriptive statistics, qualitative data is open to interpretation and needs a more careful approach to stay objective (Pereira, 2023).
I found the idea of coding qualitative data particularly interesting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 7</title>
      <link>/post/m7u7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u7/</guid>
      <description>Inferential Statistics and Hypothesis Testing This week is formative assessment week! Indeed, the literature review is due at the end of this unit. I am not entirely sure how I feel about my submission. I think I did okay but I guess I won&amp;rsquo;t be sure until I get the grades back.
I will reflect very little this week as the e-Portfolio assessment is quite comprehensive. We have had to do a lot of Excel exercises.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 6</title>
      <link>/post/m7u6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u6/</guid>
      <description>Quantitative Methods - Descriptive and Inferential Statistics Half way there! This week actually brings me some much needed relief. The doubling-up of modules is finally over. I have managed to submit my last assignment in my other module. This means I can solely focus on this module for the next six weeks.
This week, we explored the world of quantitative methods. I learned that quantitative methods investigate the relationships between variables that are measured numerically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 5</title>
      <link>/post/m7u5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u5/</guid>
      <description>Interviews, Survey Methods, and Questionnaire Design This week, we explored the world of interviews, survey methods, and questionnaires. I did not learn this during this unit, but it was reinforced that interviews can provide good feedback via the one-on-one conversation medium. This allows researchers to gather detailed and qualitative data. On the other hand, online surveys, are a quantitative method used to gather opinions and trends from a much larger sample.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 12</title>
      <link>/post/m6u12/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u12/</guid>
      <description>The Case for the Future Direction of Software Engineering Project Management Final week of this module! Time flies! I can&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;rsquo;s already been 12 weeks. This module just flew by.
I have appreciated this module in its entirety. Even though I did mention in unit 1 that I don&amp;rsquo;t particularly envisage a career in product management. The module was well structured and definitely kept me busy. We had a lot of materials and activities to complete, and I can assure you that I spent a few nights understanding how everything fit together.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 11</title>
      <link>/post/m6u11/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u11/</guid>
      <description>Software Engineering Project Management: Future Trends Welcome to unit 11, the next to last for this module. This week, I&amp;rsquo;ll mainly reflect on the assignment that I had to submit.
Following the group task assignment in unit 6, we were now given the assignment of a follow-up meeting happening 12 months later. The meeting is to give a project update to the main stakeholders. This was an individual task. We had to record a 20 minute presentation while also providing a full transcript of the video.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 4</title>
      <link>/post/m7u4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u4/</guid>
      <description>Case Studies, Focus Groups and Observations Reflecting on unit 4, I am only now starting to understand how much work I will need to put in for my capstone project. There are some many things to consider, research and think about. I have to admit that right now, it feels quite overwhelming.
This week, we explored case studies and focus groups. I like the idea of focus groups and I&amp;rsquo;d love to have at least one in my capstone project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 10</title>
      <link>/post/m6u10/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u10/</guid>
      <description>Software Quality Monitoring in Python Again, for this unit, I won&amp;rsquo;t reflect with a lot of words, I think it&amp;rsquo;s better to keep focused on the activity below.
Activity: Using Linters to Achieve Python Code Quality We were tasked with analysing some python code using different linters.
I have run the code through four linters as suggested, but I also researched the latest on the web, and I saw that Ruff (docs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 3</title>
      <link>/post/m7u3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u3/</guid>
      <description>Methodology and Research Methods I started this third week a bit stressed. For the next 3/4 weeks, the doubling-up of modules is coming right back at me. I have two assignments to give back for my other module and lots of reading and formative activities for this module.
In this unit, I have learned the difference between Exploratory Research and Conclusive Research. As mentioned previously, new concepts to me. If I had to resume briefly, exploratory research investigates a problem that is not yet clearly defined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 9</title>
      <link>/post/m6u9/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u9/</guid>
      <description>Quality Management Strategy I won&amp;rsquo;t reflect much on this unit as I&amp;rsquo;d rather focus on the python exercise, but overall, this week provided various metrics and strategies for quality management. I also learned about the critical role of planning to prevent technical debt and to ensure the delivery of high quality software.
## e-Portfolio Activity: Improving Code Quality
This is some example of some old code that I wrote in the past:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 2</title>
      <link>/post/m7u2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u2/</guid>
      <description>Research Questions, the Literature Review and the Research Proposal Believe it or not, but, if doubling-up on two modules at the same time wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough, I&amp;rsquo;ve just been told that I will have to travel for two weeks to the US for work. This is now a recurring theme, in past modules, I&amp;rsquo;ve been traveling at the exact same time as when assignments were due. I guess this module will be no different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 8</title>
      <link>/post/m6u8/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u8/</guid>
      <description>Python Data Structures Data structures, here we go! In previous modules, I have already explored a few of Python&amp;rsquo;s data structures. If I had to list my favourite four, they would be:
Lists - They are quite versatile and easy to use. Dictionaries - We can&amp;rsquo;t go wrong with key-value pairs storage. Dictionaries also allow for fast searching. Sets - Super useful for storing unique items. Tuples - Perfect for immutable sequences such as records that shouldn’t be modified.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Methods and Professional Practice - Unit 1</title>
      <link>/post/m7u1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m7u1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to Research Methods. The Scientific Investigation and Ethics in Computing I cannot believe I am typing this, but this is the very first unit of my last taught module at the University of Essex Online.
Time has flown by, and I can&amp;rsquo;t believe I have been studying for more than a year and a half now.
This new module is a bit different from all the previous ones, as we will be focusing more on research methods in order to prepare us for our Capstone projects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 7</title>
      <link>/post/m6u7/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u7/</guid>
      <description>Software Development Life Cycles In unit 7, we focused on the many aspects of the Software Development Life Cycles (SDLCs) and their overall impact on project management. The two main focus points were the Waterfall and Agile methodologies. I have had exposure to both methodologies, but I am by no means an expert. In our previous group task, we decided to use the Waterfall approach (which I personally think is quite outdated), I&amp;rsquo;d have rather used the Agile approach which fits more with my approach of doing things, small iterations that always give the user a bit more than what they had before.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 6</title>
      <link>/post/m6u6/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u6/</guid>
      <description>pytest and Test-Driven Development Welcome to unit 6 reflections! We&amp;rsquo;re now halfway through this module which also means that it&amp;rsquo;s assessment week.
Last week we were given an introduction to testing, but this week is where all the meat is.
This week provided a good balance between theoretical and practical work. I have really enjoyed the pytest activity.
I have managed to make all the tests fail as per the requirements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 5</title>
      <link>/post/m6u5/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u5/</guid>
      <description>User Experience In unit 5, we explored User Experience (UX), and realistically, I knew nothing about UX so I was hoping to learn a lot this week.
When I first opened the unit page on the university learning web app, I did not understand why we had a whole unit on UX in a project management module. However, after this week, I appreciate the learning. Project management is a multifaceted role, so it became clear that a project manager is also responsible to orchestrate all the UX efforts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 4</title>
      <link>/post/m6u4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u4/</guid>
      <description>Estimating Tools and Risk Assessment As I reflect on unit 4, I am starting to feel that I am getting a bit better on all things related to project management. This week, I have enjoyed the more recent reading materials, it&amp;rsquo;s a nice change from reading about project management in the 1970s.
In this unit, I met with my fellow group students for the first time. You&amp;rsquo;d think that with a deadline due in two weeks we would have met sooner, but no.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 3</title>
      <link>/post/m6u3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u3/</guid>
      <description>Estimating, Planning and Risk In unit 3, we explored some more concepts in the project management space, such as estimation, planning, and risk. The unit highlighted and explored the importance of accurate estimation, proper planning, and comprehensive risk assessment in software project management.
e-Portfolio Activity: Data Structures Reflection As I use the UoEO platform nearly every day, I thought I would analyse and reflect on it. If I were to build something similar myself, this is how I would do it:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 2</title>
      <link>/post/m6u2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u2/</guid>
      <description>Study: Why Projects Fail and Gathering Requirements Exercise Week number two, here we go. Unit 2 had a strong emphasis on exploring and reading why projects fail. I mean, just type in into Google: why do projects fail in project management and you&amp;rsquo;ll have more reading material than you can ingest for the next decade:
After reading the given materials and also researching on my own, it&amp;rsquo;s becoming quite clear to me why projects fail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management</title>
      <link>/post/module_six/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/module_six/</guid>
      <description>Welcome back to my e-portfolio and to the Software Engineering Project Management module!
As usual, here&amp;rsquo;s a small extract from the course&amp;rsquo;s website:
In this module, you will be exposed to what it means to be a Project Manager of a software engineering project. We will examine the relationships between the Project Manager and the other stakeholders in a project, and the role that the Project Manager has in ensuring that the triple constraints of project management are balanced, and any technical debt is not accrued.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering Project Management - Unit 1</title>
      <link>/post/m6u1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m6u1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to Software Engineering Project Management Welcome to the Software Engineering Project Management module!
This module introduces us to the concept of Project Management. Full disclaimer: I do not intend to become a PM, but I still believe it would be beneficial for me to understand how the world of project management works. Understanding both sides of the equation is always beneficial.
This unit provided a solid introduction to the role of a Software Engineering Project Manager (SEPM) and how it differs from traditional project management.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 1 </title>
      <link>/post/m3u1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u1/</guid>
      <description>Unit 1: Introduction to Secure Software Development And we&amp;rsquo;re back! After a two week pause from the previous module, we&amp;rsquo;re kicking off the first unit with software development methodologies. The agile methodology, with its popular adaptability, stands out as particularly useful for embedding security within the software development lifecycle.
I came across a paper that, despite being a few years old, offered insightful perspectives on integrating security practices within agile frameworks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 10</title>
      <link>/post/m3u10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u10/</guid>
      <description>Unit 10: From Distributed Computing to Microarchitectures Hello from Week 10! I can’t believe how time has flown. This week was all bout distributed computing and microarchitectures. Work is still keeping me busy in the US but I&amp;rsquo;m enjoying it quite a lot.
This week we dove deep into the variety of system architectures – from the good old monolithic deployments to the modern, sleek microservices, not forgetting virtualisation and containers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 11</title>
      <link>/post/m3u11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u11/</guid>
      <description>Unit 11: Future trends in Secure Software Development Hello and welcome to Week 11! We&amp;rsquo;re in the final run of this module now! Exciting!
This week, we&amp;rsquo;re looked into the future, exploring the up-and-coming trends in secure software development.
We’ve talked about a lot of different topics in this module, but this week, it’s like we’re looking through a telescope, catching a glimpse of what’s on the horizon in terms of secure design, development practices, programming languages, and operating systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 12</title>
      <link>/post/m3u12/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u12/</guid>
      <description>Unit 12: The Great Tanenbaum-Torvalds Debate Revisited Welcome to the grand finale of our SSD journey, Week 12!
In the concluding week of this module, we revisited the historic Tanenbaum-Torvalds debate: monolithic and microkernel-based operating systems.
Tanenbaum championed microkernels for their modularity and fault isolation, while Torvalds demonstrated the practical efficiency of monolithic kernels with Linux. The 1992 hardware limitations framed their discussions, starkly contrasting today’s cloud-centric, security-threatened environment.
Our readings, including works by Biggs et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 2</title>
      <link>/post/m3u2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u2/</guid>
      <description>Unit 2: Exploring Software Security and UML Flow Charts Hello again! We’ve now fully back into study mode in this second week. This week we further looked into Agile and Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC). This week I also wrote my UML flow chart and posted on the University&amp;rsquo;s forum to discuss my findings. As discussed in the last unit, I choose BOLA. I&amp;rsquo;ve attached my Initial Post below if you want to read it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 3</title>
      <link>/post/m3u3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u3/</guid>
      <description>Unit 3: Programming Languages: History, Concepts &amp;amp; Design Hi! This third week has been great! We explored the history, concepts, and designs of programming languages.
We started the week with a journey through the evolution of programming languages. It was like time traveling, from the early days of machine code and assembly language with the SSEM and Cambridge EDSAC, all the way to the iconic 1950s with the birth of Cobol, Fortran, Lisp, and ALGOL.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 3</title>
      <link>/post/m3u4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u4/</guid>
      <description>Unit 4: Exploring Programming Language Concepts Welcome back! In Week 4, we explored the interplay between key programming concepts and system security, focusing on regular expressions and recursion.
I was amazed to see how powerful yet potentially dangerous regular expressions can be. Learning about their ability to cause ReDoS attacks opened my eyes to the importance of careful implementation. It’s clear that while they are indispensable for text manipulation, they require a thoughtful approach to ensure security.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 3</title>
      <link>/post/m3u5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u5/</guid>
      <description>Unit 5: An Introduction to Testing Wow, week 5 already! Time flies! This week, we were challenged with software testing. It’s been a bit tough, trying to get my head around all the testing lingo, different techniques, and tools out there.
We’ve covered a lot of material, from setting up a solid test plan and understanding the standards in the industry to digging into a bunch of testing methods.
After this week, I feel more confident to:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 3</title>
      <link>/post/m3u6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u6/</guid>
      <description>Unit 6: Using Linters to Support Python Testing Week 6! We&amp;rsquo;re half way there!
This week, I studied linters and their vital part in enhancing Python code quality. While linters don&amp;rsquo;t make your code better per say, they definitely help you in your day to day job and take away some cognitive load to help you better focus on the code.
Working with various linters, I discovered that while they aim to achieve similar goals, each has its unique strengths and applicability in different scenarios.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 7</title>
      <link>/post/m3u7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u7/</guid>
      <description>Unit 7: Introduction to Operating Systems Week 7, here we go! This week was all about Operating Systems (OS) and how they play with programming languages and security.
Operating Systems, are like the backstage crew of a rock concert. You don’t see them, but they make sure everything runs smoothly. This week, I got to learn how applications talk to OS for things like getting keyboard input or showing elements on the screen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 8</title>
      <link>/post/m3u8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u8/</guid>
      <description>Unit 8: Cryptography and Its Use in Operating Systems We&amp;rsquo;re now in the final units for this module. On a personal level, I know that the upcoming 4 weeks will be challenging. Work wants me in the US for the next few weeks as we&amp;rsquo;re planning next&amp;rsquo;s year roadmap. Unfortunately, this is when this course picks up and you have to hand over a few marked assignments. However, I&amp;rsquo;ll do my best to keep everything under control!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 - Unit 9</title>
      <link>/post/m3u9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m3u9/</guid>
      <description>Unit 9: Developing an API for a Distributed Environment If you thought the past weeks were intense, brace yourself! Week 9 has thrown me right into the thick of developing APIs for a distributed environment. With work in the US and my studies ramping up, it’s been a tough week, but hey, what&amp;rsquo;s life without a challenge or two?
Diving right into the nitty-gritty, we looked at CRUD capabilities in Python.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Secure Software Development</title>
      <link>/post/module_three/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/module_three/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to module 3! Here are another 12 weeks of self reflection, broken down by units.
Below is a small extract for this module directly from the course&amp;rsquo;s website:
In this module, we’ll take an in depth look at the security risks which are associated with programming languages, from the perspectives of design and architecture approaches, programming paradigms, testing, the impact and implications of operating systems and libraries on software development, the security risks associated with distributed systems and APIs, and future trends in secure software and systems design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Final Reflection</title>
      <link>/post/m2_final_reflection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2_final_reflection/</guid>
      <description>Final Reflection Introduction What a module! I won&amp;rsquo;t lie, it&amp;rsquo;s been a long twelve weeks. In between work and the sheer amount of work expected in this module, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have much time to relax. In the first few weeks, I found myself learning more about Python, Object-Oriented Programming (OOP), UML diagrams and the subtle art of writing sustainable and maintainable code. I had no idea what UML was and I struggled to understand its core concepts at the beginning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 1 </title>
      <link>/post/m2u1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u1/</guid>
      <description>An Introduction to Python Programming and the OO Programming Paradigm The first week of module two has been a real eye-opener. The learning materials we&amp;rsquo;ve been given are packed with everything you need to know about object-oriented programming (OOP), from its core concepts to its historical development. In the 2021 paper by Di Silvestro &amp;amp; Nadir, they talk about using ePortfolios to promote deeper, more reflective learning, which is something traditional education often overlooks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 10</title>
      <link>/post/m2u10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u10/</guid>
      <description>Testing Code in Practice I started week 10 by keeping my promise. I posted on the Unit 8 forum, I actually posted two messages. The first message was replying to a fellow student. I managed to critically respond and pinpoint a potential flaw in their discussion. I brought to light the vulnerabilities of IoT systems and how it could potentially impact the systems and brand reputation. The second message was my initial post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 11</title>
      <link>/post/m2u11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u11/</guid>
      <description>Pointers, References &amp;amp; Memory, and Design Patterns Week 11! Assigment week!
I managed to submit my design implementation assignment on time! I won&amp;rsquo;t lie, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy about it. Again, work has been busy and stressful, so having completed the assignment is a total relief. Reflecting on this, I believe I managed to fullfill the requirements I designed a couple of weeks ago. It was nice to be able to turn the UML diagrams into a working python application.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 12</title>
      <link>/post/m2u12/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u12/</guid>
      <description>Working with Design Patterns to Structure Code That&amp;rsquo;s it, we&amp;rsquo;ve reached the final week of this module!
I&amp;rsquo;m still in the US with work, and if I am being completely honest, I need to work on my studies a bit harder. I barely touched the final reflection piece. It should be 1000 words so I really need to focus so that I can submit it in time.
In this unit, there was some interesting reading materials, from Factory design pattern to reusable object-oriented software!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 2</title>
      <link>/post/m2u2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u2/</guid>
      <description>Object Oriented Analysis - Initial Steps towards Programming in Python The second unit of this module had us diving headfirst into the nuts and bolts of how actors interact with software. We also explored functional requirements that shape these interactions. The high point for me was designing use case diagrams and state machine diagrams. These diagrams really help give a clear and concise snapshot on how systems behave and interact with each others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 3</title>
      <link>/post/m2u3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u3/</guid>
      <description>UML The third week of the module was all about getting to know the Unified Modelling Language (UML). I have to be honest, I had never heard of it prior to starting this unit. However, the deeper I studied UML&amp;rsquo;s shared syntax and models, the clearer it became how useful it is in making sure everyone is on the same page when designing an application.
One thing that really caught my attention was how different UML models come into play at different stages of the Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 4</title>
      <link>/post/m2u4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u4/</guid>
      <description>UML In Week 4, I dug deeper into the world of UML models. This fourth unit introduced class diagrams. Class diagrams are quite important as they show the structure of a system, its classes, their methods, and how each object relates to each other.
As the week progressed, it felt like these UML diagrams were the blueprints, and I was the builder turning them into actual code. It was pretty cool to see how an abstract idea in a UML diagram could become a fully working software system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 5</title>
      <link>/post/m2u5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u5/</guid>
      <description>More on Classes In unit 5, I explored deeper into Python and object-oriented programming (OOP). The readings helped me with concepts like abstract classes and constructors.
I also explored polymorphism and composition. These concepts opened my perspective on how to make my code more modular. I found namespaces and packages interesting, as they help avoid naming clashes. I had no idea this was a thing in Python.
Another week and another ton of learning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 6</title>
      <link>/post/m2u6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u6/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Methods and Interfaces Unit 6, we&amp;rsquo;re half way there! This week was all about interfaces in Python. I discovered that interfaces are fundamental for designing good classes. They help keep things consistent and well-encapsulated. To go the extra mile, I also read another realpython.com article on Python Interfaces (Python, n.d.).
In Chapter 9 of &amp;ldquo;Python 3 Object-oriented Programming&amp;rdquo; (3rd ed., Packt Publishing, 2018), Philips introduces decorators as a tool for modifying the behaviour of functions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 7</title>
      <link>/post/m2u7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u7/</guid>
      <description>Debugging / Error Handling, Data Structures and Data Search Week seven was all about bugs 🐛 and debugging. It was about understanding how, when and why they crawl into my code and the best ways to boot them out. Honestly, getting hands-on with different error types felt like developing a sixth sense for catching where my code needed a little extra attention.
I learned about linters, too - they&amp;rsquo;re like those grammar apps, but for Python code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 8</title>
      <link>/post/m2u8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u8/</guid>
      <description>Data Structures and Data Search in Practice This week I was looking into set operations and linear data search techniques. I got to see first-hand how set operations like union, intersection, and others work when handling complex data. I can see how I would apply set operations in my driverless car system design and more specifically in sensors data. This would need to store and handle lots of data so it seems like a perfect match from what I learned.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 - Unit 9</title>
      <link>/post/m2u9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/m2u9/</guid>
      <description>Packaging and Testing During week 9, I looked into the less flashy, but no less important, side of programming: packaging, documenting, and testing. These aren&amp;rsquo;t just box-ticking exercises – they&amp;rsquo;re pivotal for maintaining and improving my work effectively.
I learned that packaging my Python programs is crucial for distributing software easily. I spent some time with the Python Enhancement Proposals, PEP8 and PEP257, and the message was clear – writing clean, readable and tested code is a big deal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Object Oriented Design</title>
      <link>/post/module_two/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/module_two/</guid>
      <description>Here are another 12 weeks of self reflection, broken down by units. I&amp;rsquo;ve written them in a pretty informal way.
I hope each reflection will give you some insight into my studies.
Below is a small extract from the course&amp;rsquo;s website:
In this module, we will use the Python programming language to support the design and development of object oriented programs. The object oriented analysis and design process will be supported using the Unified Modelling Language (UML).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Launching into Computer Science</title>
      <link>/post/module_one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/module_one/</guid>
      <description>Coming soon 🚧
Unit 1 Unit 2 Unit 3 Unit 4 Unit 5 Unit 6 Unit 7 Unit 8 Unit 9 Unit 10 Unit 11 Unit 12 </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
